Chapter One MORTIMER

Mortimer waited on the cool stone basement floor in front of mouse door number four, his fluffy orange body covering as much territory as it could. His paws were spread in front of him, as if he were about to catch a watermelon.

Books, in Mortimer’s opinion, got it wrong about cats. In books, cats were usually stuck-up, sometimes even uncaring. As if cats had no feelings at all.

Cats had hearts, too.

Feelings, his heart said.

Mortimer had a lot of feelings. What he didn’t have were a lot of words.

Mice were better with words than he was. Mice talked a lot.

The bell on top of Martinville Town Hall began to ring, as it did at 6:00 P.M. every day. The scratching behind the door was getting louder. A mouse would be coming through any second now.

“Apples!” he heard a small voice say. “I smell apples!” And behind the voice there were murmurs of excitement.

Here they come, Mortimer thought. He put on what he hoped was a gentle smile just as the first of the mice emerged, shaking off little bits of dirt and sawdust and, as usual, talking.

“Is that a … cat?”

A second mouse appeared. “What sort of terrible place is this, with a heartless cat standing by the door? This must be a bad dream!”

A third mouse popped through the hole. Mice, Mortimer knew, rarely traveled alone.

“Welcome!” Mortimer said. He glanced nervously at the potato bin. Last week, a mouse had managed to jump into it. Mortimer had had to wait for him, remaining perfectly still under the stairs, for almost three hours.

“Please follow me, mice.” Mortimer tried to sound cheerful. “This way to outside!”

“But we just got inside!” one of them whined.

Using his outstretched arms like windshield wipers, Mortimer herded them to a small mouse hole in another corner of the basement (also known as mouse door number three). Mice, he’d learned, never liked to go out the same way they had come in.

“That horrible cat has six-toed feet! How terrifying!”

“Wait a minute. Could this cat be the Six-Toed Grouch?”

The exit, which was not far from the old library book cart, led outdoors, away from Ms. Scoggin, the apples, and Mr. Brock’s cheese. And the potato bin.

“And now I suppose we are expected to go straight out into the cold again?”

In fact, seeing Mortimer and his sizable paws, the three of them were already crowding around the mouse hole, trying to leave.

“Not cold,” Mortimer said. “It’s summertime. Be careful, though—there’s a road on the other side of this door. Cars. But everything is fine!”

“Oh, great,” one of them said. “Thanks for nothing, Six-Toed Grouch.” And he disappeared through the hole.

“And by the way, everything is NOT fine,” the last mouse added. “I’m VERY hungry.” But, keeping her eyes on Mortimer’s paws (he actually did have six toes on each), the mouse squeezed herself through the hole, backward.

“Sorry,” Mortimer said. “Keep moving, please. Sorry!”

“Cats are never sorry,” said the mouse, just before vanishing into the night. “Everyone knows that cats have no feelings.”

Mortimer didn’t say anything. There was no point, because they were gone. He pressed his eye to the small hole, looking to see that they had made it safely across the road. “Goodbye,” he whispered. “Goodbye and good luck.”

Ms. Scoggin did not tolerate mice. By now, Mortimer knew that he couldn’t stop them from coming in through the mouse holes (he’d carefully numbered them, mouse doors one through five). The mice had been coming for all the years he’d lived in the house, and there wasn’t much he could do about it, other than gently guide them back outside again. He’d learned to hear their scritching and scratching and was always ready to meet them at a door and point them to the nearest exit.

Mortimer did not think of himself as good with words, but his hearing was excellent.

He tried to straighten up the basement. As usual, rushing around the way they did, the mice had banged into things. Tonight, three apples had fallen from a tall wobbly shelf. Even with twenty-four toes, Mortimer could not pick up apples. But he could roll them to a spot near the stairs, where Al would be sure to see them right away. He lined them up for her.

Maybe they were not too bruised. Or she could make applesauce. Again.

When the basement was neat and quiet, he took a deep breath, savoring the smell of apple muffins that floated down the kitchen stairs. Al was baking, as she did most Sundays. Through one of the small, high basement windows, he saw the day’s light fading. He exhaled, and felt happy.

Then his eye fell upon the cart of old library books. His happiness went quiet, and a guilty feeling wrapped around him like one of Al’s hugs, which were always a little too tight.

My fault, his heart said, for the millionth time. All my fault.

He looked away.

Chapter Two MORTIMER

Not long after the mice left, Al came downstairs. Ignoring the apples he’d lined up for her, she sat herself down on the basement floor, where she did not move for almost an hour.

She was staring at the library cart.

In twenty years, Al had never done that before.

Mortimer wondered if she needed a hug and went over to stand on one of her feet.

“Oh, dear cat!” she said, and reached for him.

Little too tight, Mortimer thought. But he allowed it.

When Al began to take the books off the cart, stacking them on the floor all around him, Mortimer closed his eyes.

That delicious book smell, his heart said.

He let himself think about the library and his kitten days.

Mortimer and his sister Petunia had loved their games. “Boss of the library” was Petunia’s favorite. The rules were simple: Whoever climbed to the highest place was the winner. Mortimer, with his twenty-four toes, was a good climber, but he rarely won. Petunia climbed higher. She had six toes on every paw, just like he did. He could still remember her face, smiling down at him from the highest bookshelves in the old library stacks.

Once, she’d somehow made it up on top of the library’s big blue doors! His eyes still closed, Mortimer remembered. Petunia was like a beautiful and triumphant snowball, way up near the ceiling. A stuck snowball.

Ms. Scoggin had stood on a chair to get her down.

Ms. Scoggin was Mortimer’s favorite. Her hugs were never too tight.

These happy thoughts were interrupted by Al.

“Dear cat!” Al was clutching her notebook. He saw that she had drawn lot of marks on the library cart, and piled all the books onto it again. Messily.

Her cheeks were flushed. “We must wake Ms. Scoggin,” she told him. “There is no time to lose.”

He followed her upstairs and then right back down to the basement, now with Ms. Scoggin floating sleepily behind them. “I was having the most delightful dream,” Ms. Scoggin told Al. “I dreamed I was at the movies! I believe it was the theater in Grantville. They have superior popcorn, my dear. You must go there. Please do.”

Al shoved a plate of apple muffins at her and said, “I have a plan. And I need a lookout.”

It was almost dawn when Mortimer realized that Al and Ms. Scoggin intended to push the library cart outside.

Outside! he told himself.

They are taking it away, his heart said.

This was a terrible idea, in Mortimer’s opinion, and he told them so, until Ms. Scoggin pointed at him and said to Al, “Did you remember to feed the dear cat his dinner? He is meowing quite a bit!”

And Al said, “I did feed him. Maybe he’s just feeling conversational.” She leaned toward Mortimer and said, “Are you saying very important things, dear cat?”

How tiring, Mortimer thought. There must be another way. Because he did not want that library cart to go anywhere. And then, before he could make an actual plan, Al was pushing it toward the cellar door, and Ms. Scoggin was right behind her.

What should he do? This cart of old books was all that was left of his first home, his library. It was all that was left of his happy memories of kittenhood, and his Petunia.

All my fault, his heart said.

And now they were almost at the door.

He cried, “Stop!” and leapt from the floor to the top of the library cart.

But the cart kept moving. Mortimer’s bulk was mostly fur. He only weighed about nine pounds.

Al laughed. “And away we go!”

Mortimer had never felt so misunderstood in his life. But he faced forward and stayed where he was.

My library! his heart said.

What is left of it, he reminded himself.

Outside, in the dark, Mortimer watched Al kneel in the grass and dismantle the library cart.

His library was in pieces. He had not been able to protect it after all.

Al sawed. She hammered. She glued.

Mortimer was getting a stomachache.

Then she pointed at a towel-wrapped bundle a few steps away. “Guess what’s in there?” she asked Mortimer.

“Do not break the books,” he told her. “Please do not hurt any books.”

“Meow to you, too!” Al said, pulling the towel bundle toward them.

He looked at her. It did annoy him sometimes, the way she assumed he had no idea what she was saying, when in fact she was the one who could not understand him.

“Doors!” she said, lifting a small square of wood and glass out of the towel bundle.

The thing in her hands looked very familiar. Then he realized: It belonged to the little cabinet over the sink at home. The cheese cupboard doors! She had taken them both off their hinges!

Correction: She had taken the hinges, too.

And now, from one of her dress pockets, she produced a screwdriver.

He went to sit with Ms. Scoggin. “Oh good,” she said. “You can help me be lookout. Meow twice if you see anyone coming.”

Mortimer sighed. He hoped they could go home soon.

There was just a bit of light growing in the sky when Al finished her little-library-with-stolen-cheese-cupboard-doors.

Mortimer was tired. He trailed home after Ms. Scoggin and Al. But when he reached their porch, Mortimer realized that he could not go inside.

Not with my library outside, his heart said.

What is left of it, he reminded himself.

Mortimer turned around. He walked down the steps and away.

My library, his heart said, still needs me.

Chapter Five EVAN AGAIN

Just ahead, Evan saw the magnolia tree that meant he was three quarters of the way to school. He checked his watch. By running a little bit, he had earned himself five free minutes. Evan loved making free time and then spending it however he wanted.

His back against the tree trunk, he looked down the hill he had just climbed. It was the “less fancy” part of Martinville: dirt road, no sidewalks or streetlights. To Evan, it was the most beautiful part of town: lots of trees and sky, and now that it was almost summer, everything was covered in a bright new green. (In the spring, Evan’s road was usually muddy, and he loved it slightly less.)

He took two apples and his journal out of his backpack. The apples were not “store apples.” They didn’t really get shiny, no matter how much he rubbed them. They were from the apple trees planted behind their house by his father’s great-grandmother, or someone like that. The un-shiny apples were lumpy shaped and kind of small, which was why Evan had two of them.

Sometimes in the cafeteria, kids said “ew” to Evan’s apples, which was why he liked to eat them before school. They tasted perfectly great.

Evan found his pen, opened to a new journal page, and waited for an idea to bubble up. Mr. O’Neal said they could write about anything at all. But they were supposed to write something every day.

He waited. But no ideas bubbled up.

Instead, he thought about how, early that same morning, Mr. Vanderbilt, who was some kind of businessman, had shown up on Evan’s front porch before breakfast, demanding a refund from his dad.

“What did you do, send them away for a long weekend?” he’d called through the screen door between the porch and the kitchen. “You were supposed to kill them!”

The mice in his house had come back just three days after Evan’s dad had supposedly “exterminated” them, and now, Mr. Vanderbilt said, he was going to have to hire a “real exterminator” to do the job.

“Refund!” he shouted through the screen door.

Evan’s father had sat down at the table and written Mr. Vanderbilt a check.

In fact, Evan knew that his dad did not kill any mice. He trapped them instead, in small cages, and then he drove them over the mountain, where he released them into some woods.

“I don’t know why they can’t stay put—it’s a perfectly nice little forest,” Evan’s dad muttered after Mr. Vanderbilt left with his refund. “Plenty of berries and things.”

“Too many owls?” Evan’s mother guessed.

“Hmm,” said his father. And he stomped down the cellar steps to his office.

His parents had had this conversation many times before.

A lot of people came for refunds.

Evan pressed his back against the tree trunk, swallowed the last of his apple, and watched the clouds traveling across the soft blue sky. They were the feathery kind. Evan’s dad had taught him some things about clouds on their campouts.

He braced the journal on his bent knees and started writing: Cirrus clouds are always high up, never low down. To me, they look like feathers, taste like hot chocolate, and smell like bug spray. Cirrus clouds can move really fast.

He knew he couldn’t smell the clouds. But they reminded him of camping out with his dad, sitting cross-legged on their sleeping bags and drinking hot chocolate for breakfast. There were always little bubbles of dry hot-chocolate powder floating on top, which Evan loved. When they finished their hot chocolate, they would make instant oatmeal in the same cups. And then his dad would say, “Let’s go find a trail.”

He didn’t write all of that. Instead, he tossed both apple cores down the hill (not littering, his dad always said, because they would be eaten by grateful animals), stuffed his journal into his backpack, stood up, and put on his imaginary cape.

No one knew about the cape. His dad had “given” it to Evan way back in kindergarten, when Evan was having trouble saying goodbye at the classroom door in the mornings the way everyone was supposed to.

Evan had kept the imaginary cape all these years. In his mind, he knew exactly what it would look like, if it were real: a red felt triangle, with two strings to tie it on. Too small now, for sure. Evan was actually the tallest kid in his grade. And he really liked school. But he also liked his cape.

He checked his watch again, turned himself around, and marched toward school.

He was very close to town when he saw the little free library for the first time. It rose up ahead of him, little by little, as he climbed the last bit of hill. Evan didn’t know right away that it was a library. All he saw was the back of it: a wooden rectangle, sitting on a pole. A new sign? Or maybe someone’s art project?

As he got closer, he understood that he was looking at a box. He crossed the street, stepped onto the grassy town green, and walked all the way around it.

Aha.

It was not just a box on a pole. It was a box on a pole with a set of small glass doors on one side.

And behind the doors were books.

He was still early for school. No one else was near the strange book box, other than a large and beautiful orange cat, lying in the shade beneath it.

“I know you,” Evan said. He did know this cat—Evan’s mother called it Goldie. In the morning, Goldie was usually sitting in an upstairs window of Martinville’s History House, about fifty steps away. Before this, Evan had never once seen the cat outside. But he was pretty sure it was the same cat.

“What are you doing out here?” Evan asked. The cat tipped his face up to the sun and blinked sleepily.

Evan turned his attention to the funny box of books.

When he pulled, the glass doors swung open easily. A smell floated out.

A smell like … applesauce? And … cheese? But mostly applesauce.

Strange. But it was a good smell.

A little handwritten sign was attached to the single shelf inside:

TAKE A BOOK, LEAVE A BOOK. OR BOTH.

Evan breathed in applesauce (cheese?) until there was no more room inside him for the air to go.

Take a book, leave a book. Or both.

Evan decided to take two books. The smallest two, which he figured was the same as taking one. He shoved them into his bag without looking at them, and then he carefully closed the glass doors. But that smell seemed to follow him all the way to school.

The cat stayed put.

Chapter Eight EVAN

There was only a week of fifth grade left, but Mr. O’Neal worked his students to the end. Everyone complained, but Evan loved Mr. O’Neal. He made up the best math games and never forced anyone to share their journal writing if they didn’t want to.

When Evan thought about starting middle school next year, he sometimes got a little pain in his side. The summer was the only thing protecting him now.

“Did you see that box of books?” he asked Rafe first thing that morning. “On the green?”

Rafe was Evan’s best friend. They’d been in the same class every year since kindergarten.

“It’s called a little free library,” Rafe said.

“Weird, right? Where did it come from?”

Rafe sighed. “I didn’t get to see it up close.”

Rafe was not allowed to cross Main Street by himself, which was why he hadn’t seen the box of books—the little free library—up close. Evan’s parents said, privately, that Rafe’s parents were “overprotective,” but Evan wasn’t supposed to know that.

“It smells like applesauce when you open the doors,” he told Rafe. “And Goldie was there.”

“Who?”

“Goldie. The cat from the History House.”

“You mean Sunshine. I’ll check it out after school.” Rafe was allowed to go to the town green after school, as long as he left before the crossing guard did. “Want to?”

“Can’t,” Evan said. “Math packet.”

Their math packets were due on Tuesdays. Rafe didn’t mention that he got his math packets done a lot faster than Evan did. Although that was definitely true.

After school, Evan dumped his books on the kitchen table, where he always did his homework. His mom walked in, talking into her telephone headset.

“Very good, Mr. Sloan. Now do you see the little green dot? Click on that. No? Are you sure your arrow was right on top of the dot? Try just one more time? Ah! Success! I knew you would get the hang of it, Mr. Sloan. You’re a natural.”

Everyone said she was the most patient and encouraging tech-support person in Martinville. That was why she was usually on the phone. Evan’s father had given her the headset for her last birthday.

She smiled at Evan and pointed to the fridge, meaning, “Have a snack.”

He gave her a thumbs-up and opened his math notebook.

An hour and a half later, he was still at the table (now covered by his books, a glass half full of milk, two empty pudding cups, and a banana peel) when he heard his father kicking off his work boots on the porch.

“Hey, kiddo.” His dad’s smile, when it showed up, made Evan feel like everything was going to be great, no matter what. Soon he would go into his cellar office and stay there for hours, but he always sat down with Evan for a little while first. He pulled out a kitchen chair.

They told each other the news of the day. It wasn’t a big-news day, but there was always something to say, if you thought about it. Evan told his dad about the little free library and reminded him that the fifth graders were going to visit Grantville Middle School that Wednesday. Evan’s dad told him about finding a family of mice in someone’s mailbox.

Evan had his journal open on the table, but his dad never tried to peek, which Evan appreciated.

“So where are these little free library books?” his dad asked, smiling again and looking around the table.

Evan lifted his math book to uncover them. They were real library books, he realized. Or they had been, once. They had those numbered stickers on the binding, like the books at school. But these were not from the library at school.

One was so skinny that it was barely a book. It was called How to Write a Mystery Novel.

The other one was a really beat-up book for little kids. A messy tape job made it impossible to even read the title. Evan hadn’t noticed that when he’d grabbed it.

He glanced up at his father, whose face was, to Evan’s surprise, bright red. First, his dad seemed frozen, but then he suddenly stood up, knocking over his chair and catching it right before it hit the floor.

“Dad?”

His father was already at the cellar door. “Lots of email to answer,” he grunted. “See you at dinner.”

Evan stared after him, listening to his big feet clomp down the steps. He reached for the taped-up book and opened it. Inside the mangled cover, there was a little pocket for the circulation card, just like inside the books at school. Except at the top of this card were the words Martinville Library.

That was weird. Because there was no Martinville Library. Not anymore. The Martinville Library, as everyone in town knew, had burned to the ground. Years and years ago.

He plucked the card out of its pocket. It was printed with columns for dates and names, one row for each time someone borrowed the book. The same name had been written there, again and again.

He flipped the card, checking front and back.

One name: Edward McClelland.

His dad’s name.

He looked at the cellar door, which his father had left open a crack. The sound of keyboard clicking came up the stairs. Two more mouse complaints had come in, his mom had told him. No matter how far away his father drove them, a lot of those mice seemed to find their way home.

Chapter Nine EVAN

Evan had an old-fashioned phone in his bedroom—the kind with a big round dial on the front. He and Rafe had bought a matching pair at a yard sale with their own money. They called them “the bat phones.” Rafe wasn’t allowed to have a cell phone because his parents were afraid he would catch “cell-phone addiction.”

Evan had finally finished his math packet and collapsed on his bed with a chocolate chip granola bar when his bat phone started to ring.

“I checked out the little free library after school,” Rafe said without a hello, “and I found this cool old book about growing tomatoes. I hope there’s no tomato disease my parents will tell me I might catch.”

Evan told Rafe everything: about finding his dad’s name in one of the books he’d taken, and the way his dad had kind of run away after seeing it.

Correction: He told Rafe almost everything. He didn’t mention that when he got up to his room, some impulse had made him shove both books deep under his bed. He felt like maybe he’d accidentally discovered something his dad was ashamed of?

“Whoa,” Rafe said. “You mean, out of all the books in that box, you took your dad’s favorite one? From when he was a kid? What are the chances of that?”

That was a good question, actually. What were the chances? Mr. O’Neal had just finished a week of math lessons about probability. In fact, it was the “probability” math packet that was due the next day. (On the last week of school, when the other fifth-grade class was building pyramids out of pretzels and marshmallows.)

“Do you think all those books are from the burned-down library?” Evan said.

“Mine is,” Rafe said. “But there’s only one way to find out.”

And Evan said, “I’ll meet you.”

After they hung up, Evan ran through the kitchen, where his mom was chopping carrots and talking to another client on her headset. He mimed “going to town” by walking two fingers up his palm and pointing out the kitchen door. She gave him a thumbs-up and pointed to the carrots, which meant “be back for dinner.”

Evan and Rafe didn’t need to say where they would meet, because Rafe was only allowed as far as his own corner, and so Evan always met him there. Now Rafe stood there, calling out questions while Evan worked as quickly as he could at the little free library just across the street.

Luckily, it was close to dinnertime and no one else was around, aside from Goldie, who seemed to be trying to send Evan a message with his endless stare: What do you think you are doing?

“I’ll put them back, I promise,” Evan said. He had stacked all the books in piles on the grass and was sitting in the middle of them.

Rafe’s notebook was open. “How many total?” he yelled.

“Forty-four books!” Evan called back.

“Did you count twice to confirm your data?”

“No! I can count to forty-four, Rafe!”

Rafe nodded reluctantly. “Okay. Start looking!”

Evan opened the top book on the closest stack, found the circulation card, and scanned it. “Library book!” he yelled. “No Dad!”

Rafe made a note.

In five minutes, Evan had checked every book. They were almost all marked Martinville Library. It took another two minutes to put the books back inside the little free library. When he had them nice and neat, the cat hopped up on top of it. It was a big jump.

“Hey, you’re not as lazy as you look,” Evan told him. “Who do you actually belong to?”

The cat settled himself, draping his paws possessively over the edge of the box so that they partly covered the glass doors.

“Okay, I’m going,” Evan said. “You can have it back.”

Rafe was still scribbling when Evan reached him. “Okay,” Rafe said. “Out of forty-four books, forty of them are from the old Martinville Library.”

Evan said, “People have probably already taken a bunch of them. And left a few.”

“Agreed. And your dad’s name was on ten cards.”

“Ten out of forty?” Evan said. “You don’t even need a pencil for that math.”

“Better to be safe, though.” Rafe shot him a smile and circled something with a flourish. “Your dad checked out exactly one fourth of the library books in there!”

“There’s something else I noticed,” Evan said.

“Yeah?”

“Every library book was returned on the same day.”

“Seriously?”

“Yeah, there’s a return date stamped on the cards, like they do at school. And the last date stamped on every card is November 5, 1999. It’s weird, right?”

“That is weird. Maybe your dad knows why?”

“I doubt it. I mean, I guess he’s read a lot of books, but he’s not a librarian. And in 1999, he was”—Evan had to think for a second—“a teenager.”

“He read a lot of books,” Rafe said.

“Yeah, well, not anymore,” Evan said. “I don’t think he has time. He’s always working.”

Rafe nodded solemnly. “Saving the mice.”

“He’s not saving them—”

But Evan was cut off by a long, loud whistle, followed by two short ones. This was Rafe’s call to come home, immediately.

Rafe closed his notebook, said, “Dinner!” and was gone.

It wasn’t until after dinner that Evan realized there was still one more library book to check for his dad’s name: How to Write a Mystery Novel. It was under his bed, with the taped-up one that his dad had read over and over. His cheek pressed to the floor, Evan fished it out and sat at his desk to open it.

The circulation card was there. Like all the others, the book had been returned on November 5, 1999. It had only been checked out once, and not by his father.

Evan reached for the phone.

“H. G. Higgins?” Rafe whispered. “The H. G. Higgins?”

“Yes! Can you believe it? In Martinville!”

“But it must be a joke,” Rafe said.

“What do you mean?”

“You know, the book is How to Write a Mystery Novel. So, whoever borrowed it thought it would be funny to sign it out as H. G. Higgins, famous mystery writer. Get it?”

“Oh, yeah.” Evan deflated instantly. “You’re right. That was stupid of me—I guess I fell for it.”

“Not stupid,” Rafe said quickly. “You’re in detective mode. So you have to be open to every possibility.”

“Right.” But Evan still felt a little bit dumb.

“How was dinner?” Rafe asked. “Was your dad still acting weird?”

Evan’s dad had not been at dinner. His mom said he’d been called out to a job.

His dad was saving the mice. Evan knew that.

In bed that night, Evan looked again at the cover of How to Write a Mystery Novel. He’d had no idea there were books like this. Could a book really tell you how to write a book? No teacher had ever talked about that, not even Mr. O’Neal.

Lying back on his pillow, he opened it above his head and flinched. From somewhere within the pages, something had fallen lightly onto his chest. He plucked the something up.

It was a picture. Evan looked at it for a while and reached again for the bat phone.

“Rafe,” Evan said, looking at the picture. “Why didn’t they rebuild the library? After it burned down.”

“It probably costs a whole lot of money to build a library. And maybe it was a respect thing?”

“Respect? I don’t get it.”

“Because, you know.”

“I don’t know. Spit it out.”

“Because people died in the fire?”

Evan’s heart gave a strange double thump.

“People died?”

Chapter Ten AL

Well, yes. Sadly. People died.

This might be a good time to introduce myself.

I was the assistant librarian at the Martinville Library on the night it burned to the ground.

You can call me Al.

I live in Martinville’s History House, not far from where the old library once stood. I moved in after the fire with my supervisor, Ms. Scoggin, and her patron, Mr. Brock. No one minds about the three of us living there—we hardly take up any room, being ghosts (plus cat).

Ms. Scoggin always says it was a very good thing we came, because we know how to take care of the house. I keep the dishes clean and neatly arranged in their wooden rack above the sink. I wash the windows and beat the rugs in the garden before dawn, when no one will catch sight of me (my invisibility skills are not impressive). I manage the potatoes and the apples in the cellar, making sure they have plenty of cool air so that they do not rot. And I cook: applesauce, potato pancakes, apple muffins, baked potatoes, apple dumplings, mashed potatoes, and, when I lack inspiration, more applesauce. (Ghosts don’t eat very much, but they do eat.)

Mr. Brock does his part. He has been, for many years, our sweeper. Though mostly cloudlike, he’s taught himself to grip our broom. The dear cat takes care of the mice. And Ms. Scoggin takes care of us, she says. By which she means: She encourages Mr. Brock’s reading (as his librarian), she snuggles with the dear cat (because they both like that), and as my supervisor, she walks behind me, Reminding and Criticizing.

In the evenings, after I have cooked and washed up, we all relax together knowing that everything is in its right place.

Except, as Ms. Scoggin likes to say, for me.

Our house was once the home of the Martins, our town founders, and everything in it is kept just as it was when the family lived here a hundred and fifty years ago. We have no electricity, only candles and a fireplace. Our one toilet has a pull chain. The children always laugh at that. (There are public tours every Sunday and Tuesday, at noon.)

It really is a perfect house for ghosts.

Sometimes we hear children playing on the porch (from which there is a short path leading to the grassy town green). This morning, I peeked through the curtains and saw two small heads pressed together on the swing, emitting whispers and giggles. “I believe it’s hide-and-seek again!” I told the others.

Ms. Scoggin and Mr. Brock pay absolutely no attention to the children or the tour groups. Last week, a class of third graders marched right through the parlor while the two of them just went on chatting, reading, and drinking their cups of tea, and there wasn’t the slightest problem.

I, however, have always showed a distinct lack of talent for invisibility, which is why I always hide myself away on tour days during the hour between noon and one. (Most recently, I have been folding myself into the broom closet.) I do not wish to scare anyone, least of all a child. Over the years, I have found many excellent hiding spots in our house.

If I were ever invited to play hide-and-seek, I would certainly be the winner.

Of course, we didn’t exactly plan to be housemates, Ms. Scoggin and myself. And I certainly never imagined I would find myself sharing a home with Mr. Brock, who paces around his bedroom turning the pages of his books. Every so often, he stops, throws open his door, and makes an announcement.

“Ms. Scoggin! This dog is heroic! This dog, Ms. Scoggin, what courage she has!”

Or, “Ms. Scoggin! They are almost to the mountain! At last! I can hardly wait to know what they will find there! What courage!”

Or, more soberly, “Ms. Scoggin, I do believe these three brothers are becoming the most extraordinary young men! What courage!”

Courage is Mr. Brock’s favorite thing to discover in a book.

He addresses his announcements to Ms. Scoggin, never to me. He is always hoping, I believe, that I am not at home. I know how this sounds—unkind!—but Mr. Brock is only encouraging me to go out more.

My supervisor, Ms. Scoggin, also thinks I am too much at home. There are so many important things to do in the world, she says.

But what, I ask her, can one small ghost like me do about the world?

And if I were not at home, who did Mr. Brock think would bring his plates of 4:00 P.M. cheese? Certainly not Ms. Scoggin. She has not taken herself into the kitchen for years. She prefers to supervise me from the parlor, where she claims the soft chair by the fireplace. Until his recent departure, the dear cat was usually near her (when he was not stationed at his window or patrolling the cellar for mice). Often, they shared her chair, which I brushed regularly. (Without electricity, a vacuum cleaner was useless). The dear cat is a comfort—to Ms. Scoggin, in particular. I do wish he would come home.

I am not a comfort. Ms. Scoggin often says that I am “a test,” which I think we can agree is the opposite of a comfort.

Over the years, I have asked her many times why I must be a test. I never loved tests and do not wish to be one. Ms. Scoggin just rolls her eyes, exactly as she did in the old days, when I worked for her at the library. (“Take your place!” she used to shout at me as she prepared to open the beautiful blue library doors at 8:30 sharp in the mornings. And I’d scuttle behind the circulation desk. “Stand up straight!” she’d say. “Librarians do not slouch if they can help it!” And I would straighten my back.)

At first, her criticisms hurt my feelings, but then I understood that they were only part of Ms. Scoggin’s gruffness. Perhaps this was what mothers were like, I imagined. I had come directly from the orphanage, so I was no expert about parental things.

Every morning, when I bring the day’s first cup of tea to her bed and help her pin on her “Librarian” badge, Ms. Scoggin greets me the same way she used to in our library days: “Take your place, my dear!”

But if I ask her what better place there could be than this excellent house for three fine ghosts (and their cat), she just glares at me.

She calls me “my dear,” because, deep down, she is fond of me, and also because ghosts have trouble remembering names. But in our library days, she always called me by my name, usually while pointing accusingly at a cart of books that needed to be reshelved, or perhaps waving a paper over her head while complaining that my handwriting was illegible.

Or to tell me that she had seen another mouse.

Or to let me know that the printer was out of paper.

Or that the balcony light bulbs appeared to be very dusty.

You get the idea.

In our cozy house, Ms. Scoggin is less concerned about dust. But when I venture down the path to run my Monday errands, she often calls after me from behind the front door. “Head high, my dear! Eyes up! Take your place in the world!”

I do try to lift up my eyes a little. But if I hear Mr. Brock’s echoing “What courage!” I know that it has nothing to do with me.

Chapter Thirteen AL

Tuesday, and the dear cat has not yet come home.

Ms. Scoggin says if I stop bringing him his dish, he’ll be back soon enough, but I can’t bear to disappoint him.

Today’s Tuesday Tour was a lovely fourth-grade class. From my broom closet, I could hear them shuffling from room to room and giggling at our toilet. Mrs. Baker, our tour guide, did an excellent job, as usual. But, as you can imagine, I have heard the “Martinville History House Tour Speech” many, many times, and so I sometimes tune it out. Today, chin resting comfortably on knees, I closed my eyes and visited one of my happiest memories from my assistant librarian days: book club.

Before I was a ghost, my favorite thing was Wednesday Book Club.

On book club days, I was happy at work, even if Ms. Scoggin had given me five Reminders and seven Criticisms before lunchtime. At three o’clock, I pretended to dust the windowsills and watched my book club members arrive, in ones and twos. Through the big front windows, I saw them get distracted by the bakery window or the stationery store with its comic book rack just inside the front door. (I had several times asked Ms. Scoggin if we might have a comics section in our library, but this led only to more Reminders and Criticisms.)

Sadly, I can’t remember their names anymore. There were seven or eight “regulars” every Wednesday. Plus the boy.

The boy always came to the library on Book Club Wednesdays, and on many other days as well. He walked the same path from the school to our library, but he wasn’t like the others. I could see that he was mostly distracted by his own thoughts, and as I watched, I wondered what they were.

At first, he barely looked at me, even when he came to the checkout desk with his pile of books. Once, he showed up with a damaged return—and he had tried to repair the book himself, with tape. He walked in and brought the book straight to Ms. Scoggin, and when she held it up, I nearly leaped over my desk to shield the boy from the Criticisms that were about to rain down on him. His face was pointed at the floor, but I could see that his ears were already bright red. And she had not yet begun.

But she said nothing. She merely gathered up the broken book with the others and said, “All on time, thank you,” before turning away. Released, the boy flashed her a look of—disbelief? gratitude?—and then zipped away into the cool of the library stacks. I stood in near shock—Ms. Scoggin, I sometimes forgot, was a very nice person! Despite her Reminders. And her Criticisms. I thought, again, of mothers. I had a sudden urge to dust the light bulbs on the balcony, just to make her happy.

At closing time, I found her hunched over the work table in the basement, carefully taping up the book’s spine. “Anyone could see that the child did not damage this book,” she said. “It was probably some brute bully. Why are you standing there with your mouth open? Don’t you have things to do?”

I gathered myself and said, “I have just finished dusting the balcony, Ms. Scoggin.”

She nodded. “I hope you didn’t forget the light bulbs.”

I assured her that I had not.

But I have gone off on a tangent about Ms. Scoggin! I was telling about Book Club Wednesdays. The club members were Great Readers, and we had a wonderful time listening to one another talk about the books we were reading, what the stories were and what we thought might happen next, and how all of it made us feel. These young readers felt things about books, which is why I call them Great Readers. Being a Great Reader has nothing to with reading great sophisticated books, or reading great long books, or even with reading a great many books.

Being a Great Reader means feeling something about books.

I had created a special book club area, with a small rug around which I pulled up several book carts on Wednesday afternoons, to make protective walls. It was our club room, and the door was always open. Actually, there was no door, only a space between two of the carts.

But the point is that anyone could join our club—the members even posted invitations, on the bulletin board near the big blue doors, and at the school, in the town hall waiting room, and even in the grocery store parking lot. “All Welcome,” they said at the top.

Every Wednesday, I hoped the boy would join us on the rug, and every Wednesday he did not. Instead, he sat at one of the library’s two long tables, always in the chair closest to the rug, but with his back to us. And he was usually in his place well before our meeting began, so that it seemed (almost) to be a coincidence he was there. Which I knew it was not.

You have probably heard that you are supposed to be quiet in a library, but this was not true on Book Club Wednesdays. We did not even try to keep our voices down, but Ms. Scoggin never said a word. If something funny was said (we liked to joke), I would sometimes glance over at the boy and see, from behind, just a hint of a rounded cheek, which meant he was smiling. But he never came to sit with us.

Recognizing his cheek smile one Wednesday, I impulsively called out his name and said, “Please come and join us!”

The boy seemed to shrink in his chair. He picked up his stack of books with both hands (it was always a stack, with him) and hurried away without looking back. I was very worried that he would not be there the following Wednesday, but he was. I never called out to him like that again.

The book club rug was our safe place, a place where you could say what you thought. One day, after I shared a particular book, one that meant a lot to me, a club member spoke up to say that he had read it already and found it extremely boring. I listened to him, and he listened to me. And that was fine.

I am not upset when others don’t love the books I love. We each have our own book spaces inside us, and they do not match up perfectly, nor should they. The club members said goodbye that day as usual, all of us feeling like good friends.

A few days later, the boy came into the library. It was Saturday, and he was there first thing in the morning, carrying his returns. But instead of going straight to the book-return chute as he usually did, he carried his pile to my desk. I assumed Ms. Scoggin’s “brute bully” had ripped the cover off another one and prepared myself to reassure him. He placed the pile in front of me without a word, and I made my way through them, stamping each one with my date stamper. No ripped covers.

Then I saw that the last book in his pile was the very one I had talked about at Wednesday Book Club that week, the one I especially loved.

“Oh!” I said, and looked up, expecting to see the top of the boy’s head, because he generally looked only at the floor. But not this time. He was looking straight at me.

He covered the book with one hand, fingers spread, and announced, “Not boring.”

And then, for absolutely no good reason, tears filled my eyes. I told myself not to blink.

For a few moments, we looked at each other, his hand still covering my book protectively.

And then he turned and hurried away.

From that day forward, the boy brought his returns to me from time to time. When he did, I knew there was a special book in his pile: a book that, for him, contained much. And I knew that when I got to it, he would simply cover it with his hand and meet my eye for a moment.

Not all Great Readers wish to be in a book club. There are other ways of sharing books, with very little conversation, or none at all.

Chapter Fourteen MORTIMER

A few people had brought a book, or two, and squeezed them into his little library on its first day. One book had been left with a sticky note attached: My 100% FAVORITE book of fifth grade!!! That book had been taken by a fourth grader within minutes.

Mortimer felt content. More and more so, in fact.

The first crate of books arrived on the second day, Tuesday, right after lunch. (Al was still bringing Mortimer’s meals to him. She also sneaked in a few tight hugs, but he didn’t mind.)

The crate was carried by Mr. Gregorian, who managed the grocery store. First, he tried to cram his books into Mortimer’s little library, but when he saw that they would not all fit, Mr. Gregorian made a decision. He set his crate on the ground under the library.

Exactly in the spot where Mortimer had made his bed. He glared up at Mr. Gregorian.

Mr. Gregorian said, “I can tell that you approve, Buffy. Good girl!”

People, Mortimer thought.

“Nothing wrong with adding a room to your library, am I right?”

With this, Mortimer had to agree.

Mr. Gregorian, after considering, carefully tilted the crate onto one side. “This’ll help keep the rain out,” he explained.

It was an egg crate, Mortimer realized. From his History House window, he had enjoyed watching the farmers bring their deliveries. Eggs came to Mr. Gregorian’s store twice a week.

Mortimer hopped up on top of the crate. It was acceptable.

Late that evening, he heard mouse voices again.

“I definitely smell cheese. I’m telling you, it’s here somewhere.”

There were only two of them this time, zigzagging across the grass in the moonlight. Silent, Mortimer watched them come closer and closer.

“You can’t smell it? Now it’s even stronger!”

He could see them pretty clearly now—they were the same size and color, but they weren’t exactly a matched set. One of them had a short tail.

“Oh, that was it—your tail!” Mortimer erupted.

And the mice froze right in front of him.

Belatedly, Mortimer closed his mouth. Oops. Now they would probably run away or start calling him names. He waited to see which it would be.

But they did neither. Some instinct had paralyzed them. Or almost, because he could see both of them quivering. The mice had sounded so brave the night before. Maybe they were just acting brave?

Mortimer took a slow backward step to see if that would release them. “I’m not—” he started, “I mean, I won’t do anything to you.”

“Finn, it’s just the Grouch!” one of them said. His tiny body had relaxed visibly, but Finn was still stiff as a board.

“Finn,” the mouse said. “Shake it off. We’re okay! The Grouch doesn’t bite.”

Finn was trying to shake it off. Mortimer could tell.

Still looking mostly frozen, Finn said, “Ha. Close one!” and smiled weakly.

Mortimer took another step back and spoke quietly. “It was your tail that you dropped, wasn’t it? And the hawk was left holding it—your tail? You escaped?”

Finn nodded.

Mortimer glanced at his own tail. Ouch, he thought.

“It’s different for us mice,” Finn said quietly. “We’re built to do it. It’s like … an escape trick.”

The other mouse nodded and glanced at where the tip of Finn’s tail used to be. “Right in the nick of time,” the mouse said. “It was very well done.”

“And your tail will grow back?” Mortimer asked.

Again, Finn nodded. “That’s what my mom says.”

Interesting.

“Do either of you happen to know,” Mortimer asked, because these mice seemed to know things, “why the frogs sing at night?”

Both mice shrugged.

“Then I guess you wouldn’t know how they all know to stop singing, at the same time?”

The mice looked at each other. “Never thought about it,” Finn mumbled.

“Is there cheese in that cupboard up there, by any chance?” Finn’s friend was pointing up at the library. “It sure smells like cheese.”

The cheese cupboard doors, Mortimer realized, still smell like cheese. “I’m sorry,” he said stiffly. “This is a library. No cheese around here.”

The mouse shrugged. “Okay. We have to find food soon, so we should probably get going.”

“Hungry,” Finn added softly.

Mortimer watched them back slowly away, turn around, and run.

He almost wished he had told them where to find the potato bin.

But that would upset Ms. Scoggin.

It was confusing.

Chapter Nineteen EVAN

Evan’s phone rang while he was brushing his teeth that night. He spit and ran back to his room without rinsing.

“I started thinking,” Rafe said. “About what Mr. O’Neal said on the bus. And I looked up the library fire. Guess what? It burned down on the exact same day those books were returned. November 5, 1999. That’s the date on all the circulation cards, right?”

“Yeah, are you sure?”

“It burned down that night, after closing. I found an article online.”

Evan thought about the way Mr. O’Neal had been looking at him on the school bus.

“What started the fire?”

And why was Evan’s heart pounding?

“I don’t know.” He heard Rafe clicking on his keyboard. “It just says a fatal fire of unknown origin. But there’s almost nothing else about it online. All I could find was one PDF of a paragraph from an old paper. Fatal fire. That almost sounds like a title of an H. G. Higgins mystery, doesn’t it?”

It did, actually.

Evan grabbed the journal lying on his bed, flipped to his mystery outline, and looked at the words “CRIME,” “VICTIM,” and “SUSPECTS.”

Maybe this was that kind of mystery.

“Hello?” Rafe said. “You still there?”

“I’ll call you back.” He pulled How to Write a Mystery Novel from his backpack and found the Polaroid (which he’d been using as a bookmark).

His mom was right—it was like a really bad selfie. There was the corner of someone’s glasses, half of one brown eye, and in the background, a town.

Now Evan realized why he hadn’t recognized it as Martinville: There was an extra building in the picture. The library.

The picture was inside the book, and the book had been returned to the library the very day it burned down. By H. G. Higgins. Way before he was famous.

The picture was a clue. It had to be. Was it H. G. Higgins in the picture?

On the day before the fire?

Evan tried to sleep, but trying to sleep was a joke. He switched on his light and picked up How to Write a Mystery Novel from the floor next to his bed. He was up to Supporting Characters, which didn’t sound too scary. In fact, “supporting characters” sounded boring. Maybe they would help him get to sleep.

Supporting characters, the book said, included everyone the protagonist came into contact with during his search for the antagonist. Friends and family were supporting characters, and so were the people living and working in the town. His own mother was a supporting character, Evan realized. So was Mr. O’Neal. And Rafe, of course, along with every other kid in their class. That made him feel good. This mystery wasn’t only about him. It was about all of Martinville.

But then he came to this line: “Remember! Your ‘bad guy’ will probably turn out to be one of your supporting characters, but won’t be revealed as the bad guy until the end of the book.”

He slammed the book shut.

What if the library fire had been started by someone he knew?

No. It couldn’t be anyone from Martinville.

Because Evan couldn’t imagine that.

But H. G. Higgins, or someone calling themselves that, had been at the library on the day it burned down. H. G. Higgins had returned this very book on the day of the “fatal fire.” And then, as far as anyone knew, he had never come back.

Evan stared again at the Polaroid. At the brown half-eye. He was starting to feel like a real protagonist in a real story.

H. G. Higgins, Evan decided, was his number one suspect.

Tomorrow, he would look for more clues.

Chapter Twenty-Two AL

I made apple pancakes for dinner, but last night’s supper was no cheerier than the night before. Then, because his broom remains elusive, Mr. Brock spent the rest of the evening gathering dust balls with his fingers and flinging them out the front door (which I opened for him). Ms. Scoggin and I both watched him with concern until it was time for bed.

This morning, Ms. Scoggin came downstairs with her librarian pin stuck to her shirt with a great amount of tape. “It was the only way!” she said, slapping it with one hand. “The impossible thing will not stay on!”

The dear cat has stayed outside with my little library for three whole days and nights now. Ms. Scoggin has stopped asking for him.

I feel the need to correct myself: The little library is not “mine.” Libraries are meant to grow, and to be shared.

Perhaps it is time for me to explain how the little free library of Martinville came to be. Well, the “how” is simple: I built it.

This is the why.

Last Sunday morning, when I arrived with Ms. Scoggin’s tea, she was already sitting up in bed with her “Librarian” badge pinned on and a dissatisfied look on her face. The moment she saw me, she sighed an enormous sigh and then started to tell me, once again, that it was time I “took my place.”

First thing in the morning! Every morning! And me doing nothing wrong! Me just standing there holding her tea! Try, reader, to imagine twenty years of this sort of thing. Would you not sometimes lose your patience? Would you not?

I shouted, “What are you even talking about? Why is this not my place, just as it is yours? Is this your house? You are just greedy!” I was shouting. At Ms. Scoggin.

I expected her to shout back. She did not!

But she was surprised, I could tell. And—secretly pleased?

She said, “My dear, you are a librarian, are you not?”

“You know I am!” I was not done shouting, apparently. “Same as you are! But do you see me always telling you that you are in the wrong place? You do not!”

She stirred a sugar cube into her tea with a pinkie finger (ghosts are impervious to heat) and smiled at me. “I have Mr. Brock. You must find your own patrons, my dear.”

I threw my hands up in the air. “There is no library! In case you have forgotten!” But I was not exactly shouting anymore.

She gave another sigh. “We must do with what we have.” It was what she used to say in our library, when we ran out of binding glue or light bulbs. We must do with what we have.

“But we ‘have’ nothing, Ms. Scoggin. There was a massive fire, in case you have forgotten, and nothing is left. What am I supposed to do with nothing?”

She just looked at me.

In fact, we did not have exactly nothing left of our beautiful old library. We had a single library cart, and the books that happened to be on it that terrible night of the fire. But I was not sure how to be a librarian with one cart of miscellaneous books.

“And it is not just you,” she said gently. “We are all in the wrong place.”

I felt very confused, and knowing that my invisibility was probably at an all-time low, I hid extra well during the day’s Sunday Tour, in the very back of the broom closet. As I waited there, barely breathing, with an old brass hook prodding the back of my neck, I reminded myself that Ms. Scoggin was my supervisor. I must consider her advice, repetitive as it was.

So, that night, I went to the basement, walked past the apples and potatoes, and stood in the farthest, dimmest corner, looking at the last library cart.

Just then, beside the cart, something moved. I’m not proud to say I let out a yelp, imagining a snake. At the sound of my voice, a furry face appeared—the dear cat! He very sweetly stood on one of my feet, asking for a hug.

And then, from my arms, he hopped lightly to the library cart.

I stared.

The dear cat was exactly where he had stood on the terrible night of the fire, when I pushed him (he was just a kitten then, barely bigger than my two fists together), along with the cart of books, out of the burning library basement. To safety.

This was after I had given up trying to find Ms. Scoggin in the smoke.

And before I finally found the dear boy.

I do not mention Mr. Brock because it was after-hours. I thought all the patrons had left and did not realize he was still there.

It was altogether strange to be looking at that library cart after so many years. Ms. Scoggin’s words of that morning returned to me: You are a librarian, are you not?

And that is when it happened. An idea began to form in my mind: I would build a new library. (A very small one.)

It had been a long time since I’d had an idea. It felt very good.

I did not go to bed that night. Instead, I sketched. I measured. I marked. I gathered my tools.

And then it was time to wake Ms. Scoggin. I would need a lookout.

I never wondered, before the fire, whether ghosts need to sleep. They do. At least, we did. And some ghosts—like Ms. Scoggin—are very grouchy about waking up before dawn and being led to the basement before their morning tea.

“But why on Earth must you accomplish this task before sunrise?” she said, wiggling her bare toes on the damp basement floor. (Ghosts are impervious to damp.) She knew all about my invisibility problems, so I did not answer by saying, “Because when I am out in daylight, people are often seeing me!”

Ms. Scoggin did not know that people sometimes even spoke to me, by accident. I can only imagine the long list of Criticisms she would have for a ghost who talks to people.

But if I had not answered them, I would have felt very rude. Instead, I used the fewest words possible and got away before anyone had time to understand that they were talking to a ghost.

“I thought you’d be pleased,” I said to Ms. Scoggin, brandishing my hammer.

She looked curious and scanned the basement. When she saw the cart of library books before us, she suddenly scowled. “I do hope you plan to reshelve these books, my dear! Reshelving is a priority. Imagine a reader in search of a book finding only a blank space—as if some bully has knocked out a tooth!”

I reminded her, gently, that there was no library anymore.

“Oh, yes, yes,” she said, waving at me impatiently. “I remember.”

As I have said, the books before us, and the cart they sat upon, were all that were left.

“I am going to take care of these books,” I told her. “It is time. That is my project.”

“Good girl. How can I help?”

You could have knocked me down with a bookmark. Ms. Scoggin was offering to assist me? I felt quite emotional. But, in fact, that was exactly why I had brought her down there.

I asked her if she could whistle.

She could.

So we walked out into the night together. I pushed the cart over the grass, while the dear cat rode on top of the books, proudly facing front, as if he were sailing a ship.

Chapter Twenty-Five MORTIMER

Mortimer’s fourth day as guardian of the library was momentous.

Early in the morning, the boy with the question-mark face appeared with his very loud friend. As things turned out, Mortimer’s help was needed. The boy with the question-mark face got himself quickly turned around in the high bushes near Mortimer’s beloved lost library, and then had trouble seeing the only thing there of any particular interest. Mortimer stood upon it until the boy finally noticed.

“Thanks!” the boy had said.

“You are welcome,” Mortimer said. In truth, he was feeling quite overwhelmed by memories of Petunia. There was no library anymore, but Mortimer had been standing exactly where the old blue doors had once been. And those blue doors would always remind him of his fierce sister, Petunia, because of the time she got stuck on top of them.

He could almost hear her voice. “Chase me, Mortimer. Chase me!”

All your fault, his heart said.

And then, Mrs. Anne Baker, whom Mortimer knew well, brought her daughter to the little free library. A small suitcase swung from Mrs. Baker’s hand. Her daughter held her other hand, although she could mostly walk by herself now.

“Hello, friend,” Mrs. Baker said to Mortimer. “I heard you were the guardian of our new library. I brought you something.” She held out a kitty treat. She often brought him a few when she led tours at the History House.

“Thank you,” Mortimer said.

“You’re welcome,” she said. Mrs. Baker always seemed to know what Mortimer was saying. He liked that.

“Book!” Mrs. Baker’s daughter said. She dropped her mother’s hand and pointed with both hands—one aimed at the red wagon full of books, the other one at Mr. Gregorian’s egg crate.

“Yes, sweetie. Books!”

“Book!” the girl repeated, now pointing at Mortimer.

Mrs. Baker laughed. “That’s a cat. Me-ow.”

From the small suitcase, which she had opened on the grass, Mrs. Baker removed a folded blanket. She shook it out and they settled on it: Mrs. Baker, her daughter, and Mortimer. That’s when Mortimer saw what else was in the suitcase: more books.

Everything was nicely arranged, with the small book spines all facing up. And inside the top of the suitcase, the word “POETRY” had been painted in big letters and surrounded by several small paint handprints.

“Paint!” the little girl said, pointing. “Paint more, Mommy!”

“Our paints are at home, honey. Let’s read now. Read book?”

“Book,” the girl confirmed. “Me-ow.”

Mrs. Baker removed one of the books from the case and opened it.

“Here’s a poem I love,” she said. “This poem is called ‘April Rain Song,’ by Mr. Langston Hughes. He was a teenager when he wrote it.” She cleared her throat, and began:

Let the rain kiss you.

Rain kiss! Mortimer thought. That reminded him of “wind tickle.”

Let the rain beat upon your head with silver liquid drops.

Silver liquid, his heart said. Yes! Exactly.

Mortimer closed his eyes so he could listen better.

When the poem was over, he opened them. Something inside him had changed.

Listening to poetry, Mortimer’s heart said, feels like looking in a mirror.

Maybe he was good with words, in his own way.

He wished he could tell Petunia.

“Whoops,” Mrs. Baker said.

Mortimer looked up and saw clouds, heavy and low. He felt a few drops of rain.

Mrs. Baker closed the book and carefully pushed the suitcase along the grass until it was tucked safely under the umbrella. They all scooched until they were underneath, too. Together, they watched the rain fall. Silver liquid drops.

But Mortimer felt unaccountably tired. He knew he was old, but he had hardly ever felt old. Now he did.

If Petunia is anywhere, he told himself, she must be old, too.

Which seemed impossible.

Mrs. Baker left the suitcase, which became the library’s fourth room.

Chapter Thirty-Seven EVAN

How Evan felt that night:

1. confused.

2. very confused.

When the mosquitoes came out, he and his father abandoned the rock of truth, which Evan didn’t mind one bit. He’d had enough truth for one day. They moved into the kitchen, where his mom had left them some soup, along with a note explaining that she’d gone on a house call to restart someone’s router.

Evan’s father was H. G. Higgins. The famous writer.

His dad had explained: He made up the name when he was a teenager. He had taken out How to Write a Mystery Novel, and read it. And he’d started writing. He’d done it: Gotten published. Gotten famous.

“Why don’t you want anyone to know?” Evan asked.

“A few people know. Jonathan O’Neal, for one. He’s the one who gave me your letter.”

Oh. That was what Evan had seen after the bus trip to Grantville. Mr. O’Neal had handed over Evan’s letter. That was the “paperwork.”

“But mostly I just like to be private, I guess. I like my little office in the cellar. I like being here, with you guys, in the house where I grew up. I don’t want book tours and interviews and all that.”

“Does this mean we’re rich?”

His dad smiled. “We have some money.”

“But what about the mice?”

“What about them?”

“I mean—what’s the mystery there?”

His dad shrugged. “All country towns have mice. I keep driving them over the hill and hoping they stay put so that some other guy doesn’t kill them.”

“But why? Why are you trying to save them?”

“No big mystery. I have a soft spot for mice. Since I was a kid.”

They were both quiet for a minute. And then Evan said, “How rich are we, exactly?”

The soup, on top of the whole long day, made Evan sleepy, though it was officially too early for sleep. He dropped into bed anyway, still wearing his button-down graduation shirt. His mind was bouncing. He’d been right. H. G. Higgins had lived in Martinville. But Evan still had no idea who set the library on fire.

After a few minutes, he sat up, found the mystery keys in his backpack, and ran back downstairs in his socks. He needed to check something.

From the kitchen, he could hear his dad typing away, as usual, in the cellar. Oh. Maybe it had been silly to believe that an exterminator had that many emails to answer. But who really thought about the actual things their parents did for work?

Evan left the house quietly through the kitchen door and tried not to crunch too loudly on the gravel—ouch, no shoes—as he walked past his father’s cellar-office window and around to the front of the house.

He fit the second key, the bigger one, into their front door and turned the knob. The door swung open. He stepped inside and closed it behind him. One more fact, confirmed: These had been his dad’s keys, a long time ago.

Evan leaned against the door and listened to the faint sound of his father’s keyboard-tapping. He closed his eyes and imagined his dad, just a kid, walking to the library with these keys in his front pocket.

That’s when he remembered the book.

The other book.

Back in his room, Evan got down on the rug and felt around under his bed until his fingers found it: the falling-apart book with the taped-up cover.

He looked at the dates on the circulation card and did the math in his head. His father had read this book at least twice a year, every year, starting the summer he was eight, until the year the library burned down.

Without even getting up from the floor, Evan opened his father’s library book and started to read it.

It was about a mouse.

And suddenly, Evan understood. His father’s “soft spot” for mice had started right here, with the book in his hands. Everything went back to the library.

His dad deserved justice. His dad deserved to be able to talk to people in town without feeling like they were suspicious of him.

Evan had been pretty good at this detective thing so far. What were the chances of finding a set of keys his own father had dropped twenty years ago? Not even Mr. O’Neal could find an equation for that.

Evan pictured the keys waiting in the dirt in the middle of all those thorny weeds. He thought of the cat, standing above them. Not budging until Evan picked them up.

Did the cat know something? He couldn’t exactly ask him. But maybe he could ask his owner.

Evan sat up, not tired anymore. He put down the book.

And reached for his sneakers.

Chapter Thirty-Nine MORTIMER

Mortimer had waited on the History House porch while the mice chose their preferred doors and quickly disappeared inside.

When enough time had passed for them to have gathered in the parlor, Mortimer scratched at the front door. And waited.

He scratched again. And yelled, “It’s me!”

And waited.

Where in the world was Al? The mice would be wondering where he was. He scratched the door one more time.

Suddenly, a tiny body popped onto the porch from the crack under the door (also known as mouse door number one).

“What’s taking so long?” Flavia demanded. “We are all by the fireplace, waiting for you to spill the matches!”

“I can’t get in,” Mortimer said. “I need Al to open up.”

“Who is Al? Is she the lady on the floor?”

Mortimer stared at her. “What do you mean, on the floor?”

“I mean on the floor.” Flavia flopped down to demonstrate.

“Maybe one of the ghosts can manage to let me in,” he said.

Still flat on her back, Flavia shook her head. “No ghosts in there.”

“No ghosts? Are you sure?”

“Oh yes. My hearing is excellent. Better than yours. In fact, my hearing is right now telling me that there is a human just around the corner.” And then she sat up and scuttled back under the door. “Maybe ask the human!” she shouted from the other side. “And hurry up!”

Mortimer realized that she was right. Someone was coming down the path behind him, and then, loudly, up the porch steps.

It was Evan. The boy with the question-mark face. Mortimer looked up at him and tapped his paw repeatedly on the front door, hinting.

“Goldie!” Evan said, shining his flashlight right at him. “You must be locked out.” He knocked on the door, three times.

From inside, they heard one word. “Help!”

They looked at each other. Evan tried the doorknob. Locked.

“Should I break the glass?” Evan said.

Mortimer wanted to tell him that there was a key under the mat.

“Don’t break the glass,” someone called out from behind them. “There’s probably a key under the doormat.”

Evan whirled around. “Dad?”

Mortimer realized that this “someone” was none other than the town exterminator, who drove around in a van that said “Mission Mouse.” What were these two doing here?

The ghosts were gone?

Al was on the floor?

Unexpected visitors?

This was the problem with plans, Mortimer thought. They often went sideways. He wasn’t sure how much patience an exterminator would have for the mice’s performance. They would have to get their point across very quickly, he decided. At least Al was inside. That was good. She was the one who mattered. He hoped she would get up from the floor.

Evan and his father had found the key that was indeed under the mat. They were opening the door.

Mortimer stretched his long body. He was ready. He would get to those matches before anything else could go wrong.

Chapter Forty EVERYONE

“Are you … seeing this?” Evan’s father asked.

“I think so,” the cheese lady said, rubbing her temple slowly, as if she might have a headache.

Evan could only stare. The mice were doing a dance or something.

It was impossible. But also, it was happening.

They were marching around in a little circle now, holding matchsticks in their mouths.

And the cat appeared to be—supervising?

If anyone deserved a secret mouse dance, Evan thought, it was his father.

“Unless I hit my head a little harder than I thought I did,” the cheese lady said. She was still wearing the pin that said “AL.”

Al saved me, his father had said. It was why Evan had come back here.

Al.

AL.

If this was the “Al” his dad talked about, maybe she would know what really happened on the night of the fire. Evan had come to ask her.

But he was obviously going to have to wait.

Am I hallucinating? Al wondered.

Edward (the dear boy! But no longer a boy, of course) had helped her up from the floor, and now the mice appeared to be putting on some kind of play. She didn’t know which thing was more impossible.

It felt like a play, anyway. The dear cat had jumped to the mantel, knocked over the heavy matchstick cup with one of his giant paws, and was now standing tall on the hearthstone.

The mice dived for the matchsticks as soon as they hit the ground, and then stood between the dear cat’s large front feet.

Nine mice, in a neat line. Each of them holding a matchstick firmly in its mouth.

And then, at an invisible sign (it was actually just another whistle from Fred, but the humans couldn’t hear it), the mice began to parade in a circle around the dear cat.

Slowly, the cat raised a six-toed paw above his head—it seemed for a moment that he was about to strike. Instead, he gave the air above the mice a vague swipe. The dear cat was acting.

At this, the mice acted afraid—they zigzagged around in front of the fireplace, dipping their heads so that their matches sparked against the hearthstone.

Matches.

Al heard a sharp inhale, and realized she had made the noise herself.

Edward stood like a stone beside her.

Then the mice stopped their zigzagging and match-sparking, and lined up neatly again in front of Mortimer. They dropped their matches—all but the smallest mouse, who raced over to where Mr. Brock’s book was still facedown on the floor and stood on top of it, balancing on her two hind legs with her match in her mouth.

What a dear mouse, Al thought. (But Ms. Scoggin would be horrified—a book spread out on its face! With a mouse standing on top of it!)

Of course, Ms. Scoggin was gone. That knowledge was still sinking in. The more Al absorbed it, the more she was sure she would cry.

Concentrate, she told herself.

The dear cat had begun to meow. A lot.

In fact, Mortimer was speaking. Here is what he said:

My sister Petunia and I chased a poor mouse that night in the library.

We didn’t know it had a matchstick in its mouth.

We were just kittens.

Then everything was on fire, and we ran in different directions.

The fire was my fault.

And also an accident.

I am deeply sorry about it.

I never saw Petunia again.

The mice say she may be a monster in Grantville who likes movies, and I am going to find out for myself.

One more thing.

I told the mice they could stay here for a while.

They enjoy apples and cheese.

And probably potatoes.

Goodbye. And thanks for all the hugs.

Mortimer had wanted to write a beautiful goodbye poem to go with his speech. But there had been no time.

He knew that humans couldn’t understand him. But he needed to say the words out loud anyway: “It was an accident. I’m sorry.”

So sorry, his heart said.

“Nice speech!” Flavia shouted at him. “Now point me at the apples!”

“Please,” Fred reminded her.

“Apples, please!” said Flavia.

It is true that Al, Edward, and Evan didn’t understand a word Mortimer said. But they understood the performance.

Not every story needs words.

The humans turned to each other. “Mice!” Al said.

Edward nodded. He didn’t look like a stone anymore. “Mice,” he said.

And for the first time in many years, they were able to look at each other.

“I never even thanked you,” Al said.

“Thanked me?” Edward said. “What for?”

“For saving my life on the night of the fire—I don’t know how you did it. I found you curled up on the floor. You looked unconscious, to be honest. But then somehow you got me out.”

Edward shook his head. “I didn’t save your life, you saved mine! All I remember is collapsing on the floor and then waking up outside in the parking lot with you next to me. You must have dragged me out.”

At that moment, something fell from the ceiling and hit the ground between their feet.

Al bent down to pick it up. It was a small plastic pin that read “Librarian.”

She looked at Edward. She looked at the ceiling.

And then she cried a little.

By this time, the mice had already scattered to the basement and discovered the potato bin.

When Mortimer walked out the door, no one even noticed.

Except for Flavia.

“Bye, Mortimer!” she yelled from behind mouse door number four. “Goodbye and good luck! I mostly don’t think you’re a grouch anymore!”

On the road home, Evan said, “Dad, did those mice and that cat really just show us how the fire started?”

His father nodded. “I think they did. I’m still processing it.”

Evan shined the flashlight so they wouldn’t trip. “We have to tell the fire warden. He can reopen the case. Right?”

Slowly, his dad nodded again. “I think we can ask him to look into it. But we probably shouldn’t, um, tell him about the cat-and-mouse play. That was just for us, I think. And for Al.”

Evan agreed. He would tell Rafe, though. And Mom, of course.

They had reached their house. Evan had just one more question.

“Dad? Are we the kind of rich that could build a new library?”

MORTIMER’S EPILOGUE

At the ten o’clock movie

Mortimer sat next to Petunia, tired but happy. The walk to Grantville had been a long one for an old cat.

They were in the projector room, behind a large square window, ready to watch the movie. Below them, the audience sat in plush red velvet chairs, eating popcorn.

Every once in a while, Petunia would tap him on the ear with her paw and whisper, “Mortimer! Is it really you?”

And, each time, Mortimer said, “Petunia, it’s really me.”

His heart was full and happy. And quiet.

The popcorn smelled so good. Mortimer understood why the mice wished they could have some. He planned to talk to Petunia about that.

The lights dimmed.

“It’s starting!” Petunia whispered.

Mortimer noticed two figures hurrying to seat themselves in the first row of plush red chairs. One of them carried a box of popcorn.

They held hands through the whole movie and didn’t get up when it ended. They seemed ready to watch it all over again.

As Mortimer watched, one of the figures appeared to float out of her chair, just a little, and then quickly settle down again.

Could it be? Mortimer decided to observe them more closely.

But Petunia was finished with sitting still.

“Chase me, Mortimer!” she called out. “Chase me!”

And Mortimer did.